foreign
welcome everyone this is physics as
information processing session 4 on
communicating observers it's the 10th of
August 2023
Chris looking forward to this lecture
off to you
uh thank you Daniel and uh welcome to
this session
uh as Daniel said this is about
communicating observers and fastening
your seat belts because we have a lot to
cover in the next hour
oh so just to do a quick review we've
been talking about uh Quantum
information Theory and we've been
talking about it in the simplest
possible setting
of uh two systems Alice and Bob that
exchange information through their
Mutual boundary
and we've assumed that everything is
finite dimensional so we don't need to
worry about infinite energy transfer
across this boundary
and of course we assume conservation of
energy so there are no sources or sinks
uh in either the systems Alice and Bob
and we emphasize that this way of uh
depicting things is topological we're
not assuming any background geometry no
sort of spatial embedding which is going
to become very important in this session
um in the last session we talked about
how the boundary which I'll always call
B
it can be thought of as a channel that
comprises in qubits that are independent
and Alice and Bob each can prepare and
measure those qubits
and they can always choose independently
their reference frames for doing so so
how they Define up and down when they're
measuring a spin
with effectively a z-spin operator to to
interact with these qubits
we talked a little bit about the free
energy principle in its Quantum
formulation
and the principle basically says that
interacting systems will behave in a way
that aligns their reference frames
and that they therefore asymptotically
approach entanglement so the fep is a
classical limited the principle of
unitarity
and that's one reason for studying
Quantum information to learn more about
the fep
and so to learn more about active
inference and what the theory of active
inference says about agents
and last time we talked a lot about
the constraints that are imposed by a
limited free energy Supply on any agent
uh recall that we talked about the fact
that in the absence of sources of free
energy
uh within an agent
so as long as you conserve energy
globally that the free energy that each
agent uses has to come from its
environment that's clearly true for us
we have to consume oxygen and eat food
and things like that to keep running as
systems
and we discussed a little bit this
theorem
that if two reference frames or Quantum
processes q1 and Q2 don't commute
they have to be implemented by
compartments that communicate
classically and we'll use this
extensively today
uh but the bottom line last time was
that physics alone gives us
compartmentalization in systems whenever
the systems are complex enough to have
multiple kinds of measurements that they
can't deploy simultaneously
so where we're going
uh today we're going to
start from this place we left off last
time of the possibility of agents that
are compartmentalized
and into compartments that have to
communicate classically
so we're going to talk about agents that
can be compartmentalized into multiple
sub-agents that share an environment the
environment consisting of Bob
and how those agents talk about that
shared environment
so the motivation for this is simple
it's that what we do all the time is a
group activity and what we're doing
right now is a group activity that
involves sharing an environment what's
shown on this screen and talking about
it and
the whole post session discussion
process will be another example of just
that sort of thing
so to to talk about science at all or to
talk about any kind of social relations
or to talk about anything other than
solipsism
we have to be able to talk about how
multiple agents communicate about some
shared environment
and so that's what we're going to
develop a formal way of talking about
and there are two things to notice right
off the top about this
one is that the way we've defined
interactions of boundaries they're
effectively instantaneous so each agent
remember
interacts with its boundary with some
set of operators and what those
operators do is effectively measure each
operator effectively measures the spin
of a qubit
so this is a very fast process
I'll
the other thing
that we then need to notice
is that if we have two agents
and they're communicating with each
other classically
then they're going to be using degrees
of freedom of their shared environment
in order to communicate and that's
exactly what we're doing right now for
example we're using degrees of freedom
of the internet
to communicate I'm using degrees of
freedom in the local atmosphere to talk
to my microphone
and I'm using degrees of freedom of the
local Photon field to see my screen
so
all communication between agents and
certainly all classical communication
between agents uses degrees of freedom
of the environment and the environment
remember is the other system Bob that's
on the other side of that shared
boundary
so we're going to be interested in how
components of Alice use Bob as a
communication Channel and in fact as
multiple communication channels
and I just wanted to to quote my
colleague and friend Mike Levin
in his statement that all intelligence
is composite all of us all organisms
even single cells
are composite systems that comprise many
many different agents that are able to
make different kinds of measurements and
execute different kinds of actions and
so have to communicate classically
so we're we're talking about all of life
here as well as all of social systems
and ecosystems and such things as that
so the first thing I want to do today is
simplify the notation
uh so that we don't have to draw quite
such complicated diagrams so the picture
on the left here is a picture from the
last session it shows the structure of a
very simple agent that makes some
measurements using a reference frame
called e
and then writes some results of those
measurements to memory using a reference
frame called y
and those two processes are connected by
an internal clock that ticks uh between
the the input process and the output
process and the the clock tick
corresponds to the expenditure of free
energy to write information irreversibly
on the boundary
so the the memories are actually written
on the boundary because that's where
classical information lives in this
Theory
so you can think of this whole process
from E through the clock and back to Y
as a single Quantum process or as a
Quantum computation that Maps some
sector e of the boundary to some sector
y of the boundary and so we can
represent it in this much simpler way
that's over on the right side as some
process Q
that Maps some sector on the boundary to
some other sector on the boundary
and formally that process can be thought
of as a topological Quantum field Theory
uh topological here is important it's
not geometric it doesn't assume an
embedding in space and this will become
critically important uh later on
and
the operation of that uh
pqft requires a clock tick or it
incorporates a tick of this internal
clock
and we can do this uh because we were
able to prove Jim glasberg and and to
Nino Marciano and I were able to approve
last year
that we can always represent a Quantum
reference frame as a topological Quantum
field Theory and this just illustrates
the two kinds of Transformations between
uh Quantum reference frames that are
important we can take one and divide it
into two pieces that commute
or we can take uh
a two-part reference frame and we can
swap in uh another part
that doesn't commute with the part that
we've swapped it in for but that does
commute with the remainder of the
reference frame so here R is the
reference component of some object
identification system
and we can
swap in some different way of looking at
the object once we've identified it so
for example if the the object that we're
identifying is a box that can measure
both
z-spin and X spin then p and Q can be
the z-span and X spin settings on that
box
that allow us to to effectively rotate
the filter from this way to that way so
that we measure vertical spin versus for
horizontal spin
and that's really it I mean those are
the the ways that one can transform uh
what a reference frames of course we
could do arbitrarily many compositions
of this kind of transformation to do
something very complicated but they map
very simply to tqfts with the structure
and
um you can construct categories out of
this and find a functor that's well
defined at Mass one category to another
so it's a it's an example of an issues
of categorial categorical techniques
for solving a problem that looks
difficult but in fact it's it's very
straightforward
so
using this simplified notation
um it becomes very easy to see
uh that if we have two systems Alice and
Bob on opposite sides of this boundary
and we perfectly align their Quantum
reference frames
which is what the fep says they will
tend to do
then they become entangled
and you can see that they're entangled
by seeing that once the reference frames
are perfectly aligned they jointly
Implement one Quantum process
um and jointly implementing one Quantum
process just means you're entangled of
the two sides no longer have
um
conditionally independent states
if one Quantum process which is time
reversible information preserving
is implemented jointly by the two
systems
so a lot of things like this become very
simple when we think of
of these processes as just Quantum
computations going on inside some system
implemented by some system
and how those processes relate across
some boundary so that's what we're going
to do for
studying communication
today
another thing to recall from a couple of
sessions ago or last session
is that if two reference frames q1 and
Q2 commute
we can always join them together to form
a single reference frame and this is
just a graphical depiction in this
simpler language of how that works
and
topologically there's no distinction
between
the left side and the right side what
I've done is just squeeze the top two
green circles together and the bottom
two green circles together into one
Circle
and that just makes a simple process
connecting the top one to the bottom one
so what we're going to be interested in
is situations where this doesn't happen
uh where
Alice consists of two components
that execute reference frames that don't
commute
and so the two components
are conditionally independent they do
each have free choice of reference frame
and so they have to communicate
classically they don't share a Quant a
single Quantum process so they're not
entangled
and before we go ahead to do that
I just wanted to remind you of some of
the no-go theorems that follow from this
situation
uh depicted on the right where we have a
single agent executing a single
reference frame a single process a
single kind of measurement
uh any set of commuting measurements
that can be combined into one
measurement
and here's some things Alice can't do
and we've talked about some of these
previously
um so this is basically a reminder
but I'll
Alice can't using just one measurement
measure the entanglement entropy across
her own boundary
so Alice can't know that she has an
independent state she can't know that
she's not entangled with Bob
and that's that's a useful thing to
think about philosophically uh as as it
applies to you and me we can't actually
know that we have independent states
uh Alice can't measure her own
entanglement interview
so she can't know whether she has
components that have to communicate
classically
uh she can't measure Bob's entanglement
entropy so she can't know whether Bob
has compartments that have to
communicate classically
and if you think in terms of perception
Theory this says Alice can't know
whether Bob consists of separate objects
that behave classically
oh
their behavior can look classical to her
but she's not able to determine that
their behavior is classical because she
can't uh measure Bob's entanglement
entropy
she can't measure the dimension of of
her own boundary
and recall from a couple of times ago
that the boundary includes some sector
that supplies free energy
that Alice can't extract information
from for further processing she can only
extract free energy from
so she can't measure the dimension of
that sector
and so she can't measure the dimension
of the whole boundary itself
and this of course means that she can't
measure her own Dimension either and of
course she can't measure Bob's Dimension
because the only information she can
about get about Bob is the classical
information that's encoded on this
boundary if you can't reach past the
boundary to see how large a system Bob
is
and that's clearly connected to this
first point that you can't measure the
entanglement entry across Bob because
the entanglement attribute can only be
small if her dimension in Bob's
Dimension are both much larger than the
dimension of the boundary so that's a
condition she can't check
um so all of these kind of no-go
theorems lead off an interesting Direct
s and the only one that we're really
going to be interested in here
um
is uh the third one the one about
measuring Bob's entanglement entropy
because we want to talk specifically
about how multiple agents so multiple
components of Alice can access
information about Bob's entanglement
entropy
okay so recall from the end of the last
session
that the last thing we talked about was
classical communication
and we talked about the fact that
classical communication involves
assumptions and pitfalls and that we
have to be very careful whenever we talk
about it
and what we're going to do today is
standard practice in physics we're
simply going to stipulate
that these components A1 and A2 the
separable components of Alice
communicate classically and so we're
going to draw out like this we're going
to draw a classical Channel between them
and that classical Channel passes
through Bob it uses degrees of freedom
of the ambient Photon field or the
ambient atmosphere or pieces of paper or
email or something like that that's out
there in the environment to exchange
classical messages
and there are a couple of things to note
here uh I haven't even written down here
we're assuming that A1 and A2 share some
language this classical communication
that's a big assumption as we talked
about last time
um but I will note explicitly that
classical communication takes time
that's what defines classicality here
it's causal so it can't work faster than
the speed of light
uh this is a topological Theory we don't
have any vetting geometry so we can't at
this point talk about light which is a
relationship between space and time
because we've got time we've got clocks
but we don't have any space
but we can say that whatever passes
through this classical Channel requires
at least one clock tick on Bob's side so
it's a process that Bob has to execute
and executing that process takes time so
getting
uh the signal from me to you on the
internet takes some time so the
environment's clock has to tick during
that
and all of these assumptions bundle
together turn out to be a fairly serious
set of assumptions and they involve
assumptions about fine-tuning about the
universe being just right
and uh they should make us nervous and I
just want to leave it at that we always
assume with complete a plum that agents
can communicate classically but it's not
a straightforward assumption and it's
worth any of you are looking at for
interesting uh research projects can
look into the nature of classical
communication it's full of hidden
assumptions and surprises and things
that aren't at all straightforward even
though they look like they ought to be
so there's a challenge
so why do we Ascend this why do we
assume class communication we do it
because we have to if we're going to
talk about detecting entanglement
and
um
most of you probably know the history of
of the notion of entanglement it was
first noticed by Einstein podolsky and
Rosen uh Ever After called epr in 1935
and they wrote a paper which is Infamous
uh and called the epr paper
in which they argued that the phenomenon
of entanglement made no sense and
couldn't possibly be physical
and since quantum theory included this
Con this this notion of entanglement uh
it could possibly be a complete theory
of what's going on in the world
and Schrodinger uh replied the same year
with a very detailed paper where it
introduces among other things
Schrodinger's cat as a paradox
and he explains very clearly what
entanglement is and why entanglement
follows from quantum theory and he uses
that discussion to argue that the
classical notion of a physical state is
not actually applicable to the world as
it is so he answers the epr paper very
directly
and
of this discussion of
is currently most mostly known as the
boar Einstein debate because of course
Bohr
already in 1928 has said had said in
print that the classical notion of
causality in space and time simply
doesn't apply anymore
and Einstein objected to that vigorously
but that was 1935 and it was almost 50
years later that entanglement was first
observed in the laboratory here the 1982
picture is a picture of the interior of
Allen s that's Laboratory
uh when he performed the first
entanglement experiment for which uh he
finally won the Nobel Prize last year
and uh these days this kind of
experiment is done all over the world
and is even done with satellite-borne
sources
Ian resource
is the key to Quantum security Quantum
secured communication as we'll discuss
in Quantum cryptography and Quantum
banking the Quantum Internet all this
other stuff that you may have heard of
so uh before talking more about
these experiments I just want to uh
provide a definition of entanglement
uh entangled
simply means not separable that's the
definition
so a state a joint State Abe is
entangled if and only if it does not
Factor
into two separable states
and that's it that's the definition
and
the literature and especially the
popular literature are is absolutely
Rife with hype and various kinds of
misdurification of entanglement and and
authors trying to convince you that
entanglement is this
amazing uh kind of woo-woo thing
and whenever you run across that go back
to the definition I mean entanglement
simply means uh this simple mathematical
condition of not
separability or a state that isn't
factorizable
and that means that the state does not
display classical conditional
Independence so classically that's the
way to think about it it's a failure of
conditional Independence
and it's it's ubiquitous in quantum
theory even though it wasn't actually
observed for almost 50 years after it
was predicted
so here's what all these experiments
look like they're called Bell epr
experiments after John Bell uh who
derived the statistical Criterion for
detecting entanglement
and epr Einstein panelski and Rosen who
did this as a thought experiment and
said if this this occurs and the theory
it can't possibly be real and of course
it is real uh as now amply demonstrated
by experimentation
here's how they work there's a source
The Source produces a state that's that
is entangled and I've I've written the
typical uh what's called a bell State
it's up plus or minus down divided by
the square root of 2 just to normalize
it
but up plus or minus down is clearly not
the same as up times down so this is not
a separable stay
and this state propagates outward in
space and time
to two observers who have independent
Laboratories uh for example on different
continents in that space-based
experiment that I showed you the picture
of from the cover of science a few years
ago 2017 I think
the two observers have freedom to choose
their own reference frame their own
z-axis for measuring spin
they do a spin measurement
and they do this over and over and over
again they accumulate statistics
and they exchange their results so that
they can analyze the joint statistics of
their experiment and they check to see
whether that joint statistics is
consistent with classical probability
Theory
and if it isn't
uh to a statistically significant level
then they've been able to detect
entanglement
though notice that this process requires
classical communication
they have to make their independent
measurements in their own Laboratories
and then they have to exchange results
or one of them has to send results to
the other one or they both have to send
their results to some third party
but in all of these cases they're
exchanging some classical data and so we
have the assumption
that whoever gets that classical data
knows the language it was recorded in
and so can do a joint analysis
so I'll just show you another picture of
this experiment that's in a standard
space-time diagram here time is vertical
space is horizontal
of
the two observers are labeled Alice and
Bob
they share a Quantum channel that goes
from Alice to the source to Bob that's
the entangled state
they do some processing and then one of
them here Bob sends the results to Alice
and that's a classical communication it
takes time
and it traverses space
so this step is classical so this is why
we have to assume classical
communication to talk about detecting or
using entanglement
so now I want to represent this in a
different way
uh using our little picture earlier
we're going to think of Alice again as
two components A1 and A2
they're separable so they have to
communicate classically they have a
classical channel that goes through Bob
and they also now share some Quantum
Channel they share an entangled state
and the entangled state of course is
produced by Bob the source is part of
Bob
and their detectors if you want to think
about it that way are located on this
boundary B
or they're interfaced with the sources
on this boundary V
and each of them executes a process
that accumulates data from the quantum
Channel and communicates it to the other
Observer via the classical chat
now this picture illustrates what's
called a lock protocol lock means local
operations and classical communication
so A1 and A2 are each operating locally
on their boundary they're making
measurements locally on their boundary
and they're communicating via actions
locally on their boundary and
observations locally on their boundary
so for example
I'm communicating with my computer here
we can consider it my boundary and stuff
is happening in the environment
that's implemented by the internet
and you're receiving those
Communications locally on your boundary
on your laptop or whatever it is you're
using
so that's what local operations means
and
these protocols specifically involve
classical communication and so they're
able to detect entanglement in a bell
epr experiment is just an example of a
lock protocol
uh The Observers exchange information
about how they're going to do their
experiments they're both going to
measure D spend they're going to use
independently chosen reference frames
and they're going to look at the output
from some agreed upon source
so that's all classically set up
then they they actually make their
observations and then they classically
communicate their results so classical
communication front and back
lot Protocols are not limited to this
sort of of
Bell epr sort of setting
we can also represent a scattering
experiment as a lock protocol
so
um
here's a representation of scattering as
a lock protocol and you can see all I've
done
is uh cut that previous boundary
at the division between 81 and A2 and
I've then extended it in some external
time some
um the time that is
counted by Bob's clock not by Alice's
clock
that's what's meant by external
and I've relabeled Alice II as Alice 1
at a later time so now what Alice is
doing is communicating with her past
self
or A1 is communicating with her future
and they're each doing something
different uh A1 is is executing a
procedure that in the laboratory we call
State preparation
she's preparing a state that we'll call
in
which is just the initial state of some
scattering experiment so for example
at the LHC
uh in is some state of two protons that
are quartering around the ring and tlhc
at close to the speed of light
and uh Alice then later on at t plus
delta T
is doing a different kind of quantum
process she's uh analyzing the data
coming out of something like the atlas
detector
which is a multi-particle uh counter
that's located at the LHC
so they share a Quantum Channel
which is the scattering channel that
takes the incoming State and produces
the outgoing state
and I'll recall from the very first
session as as Feynman told us
to understand this transition from in to
out we have to integrate over all
possible paths that are consistent with
conservation of of
spin helicity basically momentum plus
spin
all the different spins that are
relevant in a high energy physics
experiment including things like lepton
number which is basically a spin
now how do we know how do we know what
we have to conserve
we know what we have to conserve because
Alice is doing the experiment has a
classical memory
that allows her to remember what she
prepared she can remember that what she
did you know back in the past
was set to protons counter rotating in
the LHC
and they had certain energies and so
they had certain momentum and they were
protons so they had certain spin
variables
uh all of that has to be remembered to
make any sense of the output of the
detectors
and so to actually
come up with a measured state that makes
sense
and very often this this memory channel
is neglected by physicists and I'm going
to pause here and let Andrew ask a
question
uh thank you Chris uh so does this imply
that every time you have a log channel
the quantum part is a like a scattering
picture like a unitary Evolution even in
the earlier epr picture is that Quantum
Channel portion always a unitary
Evolution scattering picture
thank you um
yes for
essentially the reason that uh
Define the class classical Channel
you're always assuming you have
something that's protected from
decoherence by the environment
so uh
yeah if you're doing an epr experiment
you have to assume that you don't have
any environmental decoherence between
the source and the detectors
and similarly when you're doing a
scattering experiment uh you have to
make the assumption that the environment
is not reaching in there and messing
with uh the outgoing state that you're
going to see or reaching in and messing
with the incoming State and changing it
in some way that re-prepares it
uh in a way that you don't know that you
have no knowledge of
so yes you're you're making a fairly
strong anti-decoherence assumption in in
any of these settings when you're
talking about having a Quantum Channel
does that does that answer the question
uh yeah thank you okay great
so we can think of we can think of lock
we can think of scattering as lock
of
and I I just wanted to now emphasize
that effectively what Locke is
implementing is two parallel memories a
classical memory
which as we said in the case of
scattering is memory for Preparation the
pr case it's memory for
preparation for what the experimental
setup is for what the instructions for
doing the experiment are
and we also have a Quantum Channel which
is effectively another memory it's
something that's extended Through Time
and again it's implemented by the
environment implemented by Bob and it
involves Bob's clock ticking
so
whenever we have two memories in
parallel
we can construct an error correcting
code so think of a simple classical
error correcting code
for example the use of parity bits
uh in exchanging Digital Data so if I
send you a bit string classically
and I send it to you two or three times
uh so there's some redundancy in my
signal
and I send you a parity bit
I say Okay add up your bit string and
the result should be one it's it's one
on my side uh if you've added up and you
get zero there's an error someplace
you can use that parody bit to detect
errors so you can throw out the
the bit strings that you receive that
have parity zero and say oh the
environment uh interfered somehow with
the signal or some eavesdropper
interfered with the signal that made a
mistake or something like that so this
corresponds
uh to environmental decoherence not
being a good assumption even though it's
classical environmental interference is
not a good assumption in this case
so a Quantum error correcting code is
basically the same idea I use some
feature
of the fact that I have two different
memories
and that uh I'm encoding something in
time I'm encoding multiple replicants of
something in time
to provide a way of checking to make
sure that I'm sending the correct
message
so uh I can
for example
consider the message to be my classical
memory
and consider the quantum process
as a process that tests that memory
so I remember that I need to do
experiment X and I will get result y
I actually do experiment X on this CL on
this Quantum Channel and see if I get
result y
uh
and if I don't get result y then
something's wrong
either the either I can't trust the
quantum Channel
uh or I've I've remembered my my
preparation conditions incorrectly
so I'm using one memory to check the
accuracy of the other
and this Pro
of using something about the environment
some channel in the environment to check
memory
is absolutely ubiquitous and
uh we as it all the time so for example
look around your room
and your room hopefully looks more or
less the same now than it did at the
start of this session
and that's very reassuring you know it
it reassures you that something's not
happening in the environment that's
um
dangerous and disturbing
and if you couldn't do that if if your
environment was constantly changing
and there is no familiarity about the
environment you wouldn't be able to
check your memory uh you wouldn't be
able to check your sanity
so even though we don't think about
our local environments as effectively an
error correcting code that's exactly how
we use it we use stigmergic memory or
memory out there in the environment as a
way of checking our own memories and
assuring that our memory is okay
so uh I talked a little bit about
Quantum security uh here's how Quantum
security system works again it's a lock
protocol
uh we have some classical signals that
can be thought of as a code or a key
or a one-time pad for example
that encodes a way of doing experiments
and once that's been exchanged assuming
it's secure then we can use the CL the
quantum channel to communicate
information
and the classical channel has told us
what we have to do with that Quantum
Channel we have to make certain kinds of
measurements
at say particular clock times as
measured and we'll get information
sent from
from the past
from the sender
and
the classical Channel protects the
quantum channel from adversarial agents
because anything that an adversarial
agent does to the quantum Channel if if
some agent tries to eavesdrop for
example on the quantum Channel
they'll disrupt the quantum Channel
and the results of our measurement uh
will not be
what's expected given the protocol that
we run that we have run
so
Quantum communication is secured by the
fact that interfering with some
entangled State actually destroys the
state so it's detectable
we can always know if someone is trying
to disrupt our Communications which
isn't true if we just have two classical
channels
Charlie can always intercept a message
and then recreate it and that's not
possible with a Quantum Channel
so let's refold this diagram
uh so that we've taken the external time
back out of it
and we have this picture where the two
components of Alice are just interacting
via their shared boundary with their
environment Bob
and now we can see that the source of
redundancy is not time it's the boundary
itself
just sharing the boundary
allows uh Alice's components A1 and A2
to put copies of the same information
on different places on the boundary
so the boundary now becomes a resource
for redundant storage of information
so Alice wanted Alice 2 can use
different parts of the boundary
uh
to check what other parts of the
boundary say to check the information
that's encoded on other parts of the
boundary
so they can define an error correcting
code on the boundary itself using this
lock protocol
so
I just want to leave you with this idea
that
using classical and quantum
channels together
allows us to Define
error correcting codes on boundaries
that we share
as separate agents
and
um
leave you to think about
what shared measurements what shared
Quantum reference frames
let us as agents
see the same things
and this is what we'll talk about
next time in September
we'll talk specifically about how space
provides us with an error correcting
code
and try to understand why space is
treated as emergent
from something else basically from
communication
in in most of quantum gravity
so thank you very much uh I encourage
you to use the interactive QA and to
attend the discussion sessions
and we'll see you in September thank you
awesome
Chris
thank you for the lecture
um Andrew do you have any
remarks or questions
no not right now thank you
I'll just ask a few quick questions and
if anyone has one quickly in the live
chat so you mentioned the tick of the
clock and in active inference we often
hold up side by side both the discrete
time models and the continuous time
models so do clocks have to tick
discreetly or how do we think about
continuous time modeling
uh in this in this Quantum setting they
do have to take discreetly because one
has to be able to distinguish uh Alice's
preparation of the qubits on her
boundary from Bob's measurements of the
qubits on the boundary
and uh
this process can be extremely fast with
respect to any kind of sense of
macroscopic time
oh you know your your eyes are
responding to photons in
um
I think it's hundreds of femtoseconds
so the the discrete transitions that are
effectively time measurements
for you
are at that very fast molecular time
scale much much faster than our typical
clocks
now when we when we try to do very fast
timing we're constructing a faster clock
than that but it's a clock that we can
only observe indirectly
awesome okay now this one maybe connects
a little bit to application but with all
the developments happening in theory
some of which you're reviewing here and
also in practice with Quantum
computation
and then keeping in mind this
distinction sorry I've lost you
back
I've Lost You Daniel okay we'll wait
till you're back
I can see that no okay okay yeah all
right just repeat all right motion
please
um yeah so so given these
um rapid and ongoing developments in
theory and practice related to Quantum
information science and and Quantum
information security
how are people using this distinction of
the classical stigmergic memory
and then the quantum cognitive process
to anticipate
how to develop information systems that
are reliable going forward
um
I don't I don't know of any
instances in which of thinking about
Quantum cognition has entered directly
into any design of communication
communication systems oh
the ability of humans to interact with
these systems is just assumed
so it's just assumed that the user can
interact with say a computer interface
which is the sort of interface that will
be provided or is provided to any
quantum computer so if you think about a
quantum computer
a practical quantum computer
it has Classical interfaces front and
back
so in
thinking about interacting with the
computer I'm giving it some classical
problem statement for example
and asking for some classical answer and
what it's going to give me is a
probability distribution of classical
answers
but I can
by running the calculation many times
make that probability distribution
fairly tight
so so yeah I don't know if anyone
talking about Quantum bcis at this point
it'd be an interesting question
um and
was it always understood these sorts of
blind spots and axioms associated with
classical
communication was it was it developed as
kind of like a proposal or like a
special case and and uh you know
more unpacking was left for later or are
these blind spots things that were now
coming into awareness of given what
we're learning in the quantum
information Sciences
I think we're learning how serious they
are
uh but they were certainly recognized
even by Bohr in his 1928 paper
and
um that's a very good paper too it's
it's called Uh the present state of
quantum theory or something like that
and it's in nature
uh and it's available on the web
somewhere
uh I I have a copy of it
uh but it was written uh in a sense it's
Bohr's summary of the 1927 solve a
conference which was the conference at
which
um everyone doing quantum theory at that
time
got together to talk about their results
and in it uh Bohr essentially presents
what came to be the Copenhagen
interpretation
which I
think is
probably unfairly called an
interpretation it's sort of the
the Copenhagen pragmatic stance toward
quantum theory
and essentially what Bohr says
is uh that if we're going to do science
we have to assume that people can talk
to each other
and if we're going to do science we have
to assume that there are instruments
that we can manipulate
and have reasonable confidence that we
know what manipulation we've done so if
if I turn a knob from one to two
I have to be reasonably confident that
I'm making a particular change that I
can understand
and we have to uh have reasonable
confidence that different Laboratories
can replicate the same experiment
and if we think about any of those
assumptions in purely Quantum theoretic
terms
then
all sorts of questions are raised right
every Quantum system is unique we have
the no cloning theorem so every
scientific instrument is unique
so there's no such thing as as exactly
replicating an experiment right that's
that's a coarse grained description of
what I've done with a completely unique
Quantum system
and my brain of course is unique
uh and yours is too and everyone else's
is
so talking about a sharing a language
is essentially a coarse grained
assumption
and what the Copenhagen stance is all
about is coarse graining yielding
effective classicality or what that
really means is coarse graining yielding
a description that we can use in in our
in the language that we understand
so these are very very old issues
that have been recognized for a long
time
but I think in part because of the
disaster of shut up and calculate
uh they haven't really been talked about
in the classroom
awesome I'll just read short questions
from the chat we can just uh we can pass
them to the discussion section but but
there's a lot of great diverse questions
so Alexi wrote I think I've Lost You
Again
the Revenge of Zoom well
we looked at the chart earlier where
like Bob was talking to Alice
the unidirectional communication okay
good
yeah okay okay okay the unidirectional
the third party is recording it I'm sure
um Alexi wrote uh regarding the
environment for uh being used for error
correction
a symptom of derealization in Psychology
psychological trauma breakdown we don't
recognize the environment around us and
it's scary
makes sense makes sense all right from
Bala nice presentation I heard Chris say
entangled states are locc for a specific
reference frame is this entanglement
unitary or is it related to the numbers
of degrees of freedom
um
I I think the the quick answer would be
both
uh if you have a complex system with
many degrees of freedom some can be
entangled While others aren't
uh it depends on what parts of the state
are separable
so again entanglement is just a
statement about uh
components components of a joint state
that factor or don't
so you can have a joint state that looks
that looks separable along some
Dimensions but does
know the dimensions
another big complication here is that
whether a state looks entangled depends
on the reference frames that you use to
measure it with
and if you if you pick entangled
reference frames then what we ordinarily
think of as separable as entangled
States become separable
so you can move entanglement around
awesome okay from Roland Rodriguez
is the discrete temporality only within
the context of a given holographic
screen interface with time being
bracketed otherwise Beyond interface
systems is continuity or discretion kept
agnostic
oh
I think if I understand the question
correctly it's yes uh if I don't draw
any boundaries I just have the joint
state
then the evolution is unitary
and uh in a sense time plays no role
and if if unitary
evolution is perfectly time symmetric so
time actually drops out altogether
awesome so talk about time we have to
draw boundaries
awesome time must have a stop Huxley and
I'll ask one last question from the
appropriately monitored question
quanderer
all communication is abductive is a
sentiment that I've been using to
develop some arguments does that scan
for you
how do we connect what we're discussing
here with Quantum to abductive logic
um
yeah I I
I could go along with that I'd want a
lot more detail uh
all communication is is essentially
analogical I I would agree with that yes
enter
yes thank you um uh so going back to the
picture where the scattering picture
um so we have so far everything is is
topological and
um we certainly induces you know
breaking the boundary in different
sectors I suppose it induces a topology
on the boundary now I had a couple
questions as for the geometry and this
might be getting ahead
um
is it is it an emerging property of
those channels between different uh
boundary sectors and if if that's the
case then what what does it mean to have
a qrf for space
um yeah this is this is this is really
the topic for September but uh you you
do raise you do point out the fact that
it's something of a chicken and egg
situation uh
uh the way
I think of it is I suppose to choose the
chicken side
and think about uh what kind of
reference frame
does the agent have to implement
to
to see space on their boundary
and the the reason I think about it that
way is that's a question I want to be
able to ask about biological systems and
and this actually gets into
probably what won't be talked about
until October
but uh
I I want to be able to ask
um
essentially a phylogenetic question
of what sorts of organisms where and the
lineage from Luca
do uh we find systems that are able to
assign spatial coordinates to their
boundaries and what coordinates come
first and I I suspect that that
uh
sort of discrete location names with no
metric come first
that A system can talk about for example
uh this part of their membrane versus
that part of their membrane
without even having any ability to say
how far apart they are and the that some
sort of metric representation of this
angular space comes later
and that a radial space comes even later
than that but that's that's at this
point speculation but I think these are
questions that we can end up asking uh
given the right kind of formalism
and the right understanding of what it
means to to to be able to make a spatial
measurement
so the conjecture is that uh the metric
would emerge from a discrete Network
metric of counting ticks sort of thing
yeah yeah I think that's I think that's
correct and
uh that the sort of the sort of
symmetries of space that we see
are very much tied up with object
identity so if we think about
um you know something like rotational
symmetry let's see uh
I should stop screen sharing
so you know I've got this object right
and
and I can do this and I say oh you know
space has this rotational symmetry
but for me to say that I have to
recognize that this is the same object
right I I have to implement
object persistence which we all learn to
do when we're nine months old or
something
but uh we tend to regard those as
separate things as you know we we learn
object persistence because space is
rotationally symmetric
but we can view it the other way around
that space is rotationally symmetric for
me
because I Implement these constraints
that are called object persistence okay
do you think we can understand
phylogenetics as a whole as a kind of
scattering experiment like the high
energy leuka event and then dissipating
and propagating in a very Tangled Bank
well I I I do want to be able to
understand phylogeny in exactly the same
terms as as embryology
Mike Levin and I have published papers
about that that we should be able to
view the lineage of Luca in exactly the
same way that you know we we view the
lineage of the zygote that produced us
so that's why it's it's no coincidence
that
um
during pregnancy uh the the development
of the embryo merus evolution
in terms of the parts that are developed
first
yeah this is the old idea that that
phylogen and you're not an endogeny are
are related in some way which from an
embryonic development point of view
um they're certainly analogous in ways
and uh sorry if I may ask one last
question that I think should be very
quick uh regarding that the weak
rotation I'm still a bit unsure of how
it ties to to this uh diagrammatic
notation that we had uh with Quantum
channels I'm sure so on
um
in the second session we briefly talked
about the weak rotation
um you know being a a reversal in the
direction of time is there any relation
to today's session
yeah I
whenever we think about
uh the flow of time as driven by the
input output cycle
the the input output cycle for agents
separated by a boundary is is always
there's always a sign change right my
input is your output and vice versa
so uh
when we think about the
Bob's clock ticking when Alice does
something
oh
his
direction of direction of time in a
sense points with respect to the
boundary opposite to hers
but that's only with respect to the
boundary he sees he sees information
flowing in and she sees information
flowing in that's
that's the only point being made here
about the wick rotation as an operation
right
thank you
thank you Chris
very well appreciated by the viewers and
by us so we'll certainly look forward to
reviewing the Q a and everybody is
welcome and encouraged to join for the
participatory discussion in about two
weeks on Saturday so
till next time
all right thank you cheers